A Guide to the Richard Heath Dabney Papers, 1860-1945
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Richard Heath Dabney Papers 1860-1945
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
2533
This collection consists of three shelf feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The Dabney collection was given to the University in November of 1943 by Mrs. Richard Heath Dabney, Rugby Road, Charlottesville, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
The Richard Heath Dabney papers, 1860-1945, consist of three shelf feet. This collection contains various correspondence and papers pertaining to Dabney's teaching career and the Dabney family.
Richard Heath Dabney was born in 1860 in Memphis, Tennessee, the son of Virginius Dabney and Ellen Maria Heath. He was raised in Virginia and attended the University of Virginia during 1878-1881. After receiving his M.A. degree, Dabney studied in Germany from 1883-1885. The years abroad were fruitful, for study at the universities of Munich, Berlin, and Heidelberg resulted in his Ph.D. degree in 1885. Following his return to the United, Dabney delivered at Washington and Lee University a series of lectures on the French Revolution. From 1886-1889 Dabney was Professor History at Indiana University, but he moved to Virginia in 1889. He taught at the University of Virginia until 1938, and was the first Dean of Graduate Studies from 1905-1923.
Dabney's papers tell the story of a man deeply devoted to social activism and practical teaching. Although a constant contributor to newspapers and periodicals, Dabney published only two extensive historical studies: Causes of the French Revolution, 1888, and John Randolph, A Character Sketch, 1898. Indeed, he seems, in this respect, to have been much like Frederick Jackson Turner.
The correspondence is chiefly letters to Dabney. There are some general family papers, but these are minimal. Various drafts of speeches, articles, lecture and research and notebook notes, shed considerable light on Dabney's teaching career, but are less satisfactory for his personal life, personality, etc. There is much information about academic life at the University of Virginia, controversies, and general administration.
Organization
The papers were originally organized in folders in ten boxes in a straight chronological run. The collection is now arranged in seven boxes. Correspondence has been arranged in the first two boxes alphabetically by correspondent, with folders A to Z of miscellaneous correspondence. The remainder of the collection is organized topically. Box 3 contains research notes and German study notebooks. Box four contains class roll books, exam questions, lecture notes, and drafts of speeches, articles, etc. Examination papers (1919-1935) fill box five. Box six contains miscellaneous items including bibliography card. Newspaper clippings have been arranged by subject and occupy box seven. Most of the items are dated, but some items, such as newspaper clippings, exams, and some correspondence, are undated. Date ranges are indicated on the folders.
Contents List
- E. A. Alderman to Richard Heath Dabney 1926-1930 (Box 1)
- Henry L. Amonette to Richard Heath Dabney re war experiences 1918-1919 (Box 1)
- George Barrie & Sons to Richard Heath Dabney re publication 1903 (Box 1)
- Wm. R. Boyd to Richard Heath Dabney re Reconstruction History 1903 (Box 1)
- James Gallaway to Richard Heath Dabney re Reconstruction History 1903 (Box 1)
- Henry Steele Commager to Richard Heath Dabney re Committee to Aid Allies 1940 (Box 1)
- Henry H. Curran to Richard Heath Dabney re prohibition 1930 (Box 1)
- Letters and papers of Alice Dabney 1919-1921 (Box 1)
- Virginius Dabney to Richard Heath Dabney 1926-1940 (Box 1)
- Virginius Dabney to various persons 1859-1864 (Box 1)
- Letters to Virginius Dabney from various persons 1856-1861 (Box 1)
- Extract of Diary of Mrs. P. M. Edmondston re Civil War 1865 (Box 1)
- J. R. Eggleston to Richard Heath Dabney n.d. (Box 1)
- C. H. Fautleroy to Richard Heath Dabney re Right of Secession 1917 (Box 1)
- Walter L. Fleming to Richard Heath Dabney re Research 1903-1908 (Box 1)
- Benjamin R. Forman to Richard Heath Dabney re "Open Letter to White People of Louisana" 1903 (Box 1)
- Armistead Gordon to Richard Heath Dabney 1903-1929 (Box 1)
- Thomas G. Greaves on "Direct Governing by the People" n.d. (Box 1)
- F. S. Harmon to Richard Heath Dabney re war experiences 1917-1918 (Box 1)
- Robert Hessler to Richard Heath Dabney 1927 Oct. 16 (Box 1)
- James Jeffries to Richard Heath Dabney re Reconstruction History 1903 (Box 1)
- Guy Carlton Lee to Richard Heath Dabney re publication 1902-1903 (Box 1)
- George Lockwood to Richard Heath Dabney re Reconstruction History 1903 (Box 1)
- H. R. McIlwaine, [State Librarian], to Richard Heath Dabney 1907 (Box 1)
- James P. Minor to Richard Heath Dabney re Reconstruction History 1903 (Box 1)
- Thomas T. Mumford to Richard Heath Dabney re Civil War History 1903 (Box 1)
- James M. Page to Richard Heath Dabney re University organization 1910, 1926 (Box 1)
- M. J. Peebles to Richard Heath Dabney re Reconstruction History 1903 (Box 1)
- J. Garland Pollard to Richard Heath Dabney 1928 (Box 1)
- Robert L. Preston on Ku Klux Klan 1911 (Box 1)
- George E. Purvis to Richard Heath Dabney re Reconstruction in Tennessee 1903 (Box 1)
- Henry C. Riely to Richard Heath Dabney 1931 (Box 1)
- Mrs. Joseph Walker to Richard Heath Dabney re Lis Cousin 1937-1939 (Box 1)
- Mrs. J. P. Winston to Richard Heath Dabney re personal 1920-1925 (Box 1)
- Miscellaneous Correspondence, A-Z 1890-1943, 4 folders (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous Papers 1890-1940 (Box 2)
- Memorandum concerning Miles controversy n.d. (Box 2)
- Research Papers: Copies of Correspondence n.d. (Box 2)
- Lecture and Research Notebook 1897 & n.d. (Box 3)
- Research Notes n.d., 2 folders (Box 3)
- Report on engagement at Five Forks [Civil War] by Thomas T. Mumford n.d. (Box 3)
- German studies notebooks n.d. (Box 3)
- Outline plan for History of Reconstruction by Richard Heath Dabney and Bibligraphy 1902-1903 (Box 4)
- Lecture notes 1925-1937 (Box 4)
- Notes for Lectures on Greg's History of U.S. n.d. (Box 4)
- Speeches, Notes, Poems 1879-1884 (Box 4)
- Drafts of speeches, articles, etc. 1917-1918 & n.d. (Box 4)
- R. H. Dabney: Printed articles 1926 (Box 4)
- Examination questions 1934-1937 & n.d. (Box 4)
- Class Roll Books 1889-1938 (Box 4)
- Class Rolls 1920-1924 (Box 4)
- Examination papers 1919-1935 (Box 5)
- Course papers n.d. (Box 5)
- Journal of Susan Dabney Smedes 1888-1889 (Box 6)
- Graduate Students file cards 1905-1909 (Box 6)
- Administration of Graduate studies 1930-1935 & n.d. (Box 6)
- Bibliography cards n.d. (Box 6)
- Postcards n.d. (Box 6)
- Notebook recording "Deceased Solders, 1861-1864" n.d. (Box 6)
- Map of Albemarle County n.d. (Box 6)
- Newspaper Clippings: Letters to the Press by or about Richard Heath Dabney 1894-1935 & n.d. (Box 7)
- Newspaper Clippings: Reviews of Virginius Dabney's Books 1920-1933 & n.d. (Box 7)
- Newspaper Clippings: Civil War and Reconstruction 1864-1868 & n.d. (Box 7)
- Newspaper Clippings: The South and Race Relations 1891-1933 & n.d. (Box 7)
- Newspaper Clippings: Politics and Elections 1892-1896 & n.d. (Box 7)
- Newspaper Clippings: World War I & II 1916--1929 & n.d. (Box 7)
- Newspaper Clippings: Miscellaneous 1898-1930 & n.d. (Box 7)